Welcome to The Lighter Side of the Spectrum, the podcast
that celebrates the multiple hats we wear and the juggling
acts we perform in life. Whether you're parenting kids and
teens on the autism spectrum, navigating the ever-evolving healthcare industry,
or building a more inclusive and impactful world, this is
your space to find connection, inspiration, and growth. Together, we'll
share stories, tackle challenges, and explore how innovation and inclusion
create better outcomes for everyone. Because no matter the spectrum,
there's always a lighter side. Now here's your host, David
Koffer.
Hi everyone, welcome to a special edition of The Lighter
Side of the Spectrum. I am David Koffer. I'm with
my friend Kim Kretich, and we're wrapping up a really
amazing 3-day experience. It's an inclusive surf camp officially called
the Resonance Surf Camp.
But Kim, this was initially your brainchild a few years
ago. Yeah, we had started coming with our 3 sons,
one of whom was diagnosed with autism back in
2001. So we started coming to IndoJack Surf School, and
then we
just kept coming and kept coming. And finally, we— I
invited all these families for whom I advocated,
kids of all abilities and their siblings, to make it
a truly inclusive surf camp. And we did that 2016,
'17, and '18.
And then we, and then
unfortunately our son Ben was killed by an impaired driver
in August of 2023.
And so many people reached out to the IndoJack Surf
Charity to donate in memory of Ben that we did
another
Surf camp. And, uh, and I think it sort of
helped fund the entire season for Indo Jack's surf charities.
And then the Peyton Project said, let's take— Great foundation
based in Tennessee. In Tennessee that promotes all types of
communication,
uh, specifically for Peyton, the letterboard, spelling to communicate. And
so they said, We loved it. We want to continue
it through the foundation. And so that's exactly what they
did. And if you turn around, you can see— There
we go. There it is. There's the Resonance Surf Camp.
And that's actually
a silhouette of Ben surfing. He had a great surfing
style
where he'd just sort of go like that and then
start flapping his legs because it felt like— Felt like
he was flying. He always said that. So yeah, it
was just amazing to have this continue. And especially have
such
a unique perspective on
communication and
brain-body disconnect and to connect with the ocean and surfing
and with all the supports that anyone would need. It's
been really remarkable. It's so great. I mean, and, you
know, every surfer had their own instructor with them out
there.
At least one. At least one, right? Sometimes more. I
mean, we had all ages, we had all abilities, you
know, different levels of experience.
But the
level of support is just unprecedented from the instructors and
from the families. I mean, that's what really struck me.
I mean, that's what I'm going to leave here with.
Yeah, it was originally just this
understanding that
you can be truly inclusive with all the supports that
you need. And I always
tied it to inclusion in the schools. That was the
big sort of analogy of, hey,
with accommodations, modifications, support,
you can include.
And so
that's just, especially with families
hanging out together and hanging out for dinner, not just
on the beach, but— Right. It just, everyone belonged. And
that's always been the spirit of the inclusive surf camp.
It was called Pushing into the Swell, and now it's
called the Resonance Surf Camp. And it's in honor of,
it's in honor of Ben. And it just, this feels
great. Ben's spirit is here. Oh, definitely. It's here. You
can feel Ben. I mean, you can feel it. You
can feel it. We've heard, you know, like it's, it's
here. And it's just, you know, you mentioned the families
and as you know, you and I talked off camera
just the last 2 nights having, getting everyone together for
these dinners.
Yes. You know, at Karen and Chad's Airbnb, opened up
their, you know, their Airbnb to us. And I think
that's an incredible model for this moving forward because we
never really did that where everybody came together. They might
have stayed in the same hotel and sort of some
families got together. We go to a restaurant together. This
was all, you know, pizza night and then taco night
last night. And that is magical. It was just magical.
It was magical. Yeah. Yeah. You want to go for
it?
Okay. Yeah. Stone always makes an appearance somehow, one way
or the other on the podcast.
His way. He's sitting off camera enjoying the beach. Wow.
He did such an amazing job. He loved it. Yeah.
Time of his life. Exactly. Yeah. He's doing great. So
what, I mean, so Kim, what does this mean to
you now to see this? Like, you know, I'm kind
of like wrapping up on today and, you know, everyone's
kind of leaving. Some people are driving 9 hours. I
mean, everybody's talking about how we flew across the country,
which is a big trip. Yeah.
You know, some people drove, like I said, 9, 10
hours. Because it's,
you know, an experience that
can't— should be replicated a lot. But
when you have this type of experience
and support and just that sense of belonging, that's Ben's
legacy, I will say. And
if we can sort of create that ripple effect, so
to speak, then it will just
keep going. I think that's, I mean, that's the message
I want to share too and continue to share. You
know, we've done this. I've talked about it a little
bit with other events in Seattle, whether it's, you know,
renting a movie theater, just really helping people across the
country.
I mean, yes, this is a bigger endeavor. A 3-day
surf camp is kind of a bigger endeavor, but not
really, like you've partnered with a surf school. Like, I
mean, there,
it doesn't have to be a big endeavor, of course,
but it's, it's, it's meaningful. It means so much to
the kids. I mean, that's, again, we haven't even talked
nearly enough to talk about the smiles that we saw.
Well, and the, you,
the, the words that came out, especially last year of
like, Cole, and, you know, I was like, no, no,
no. And then he'd spell, I want to do this.
And it was just, it's just so obvious.
when the,
the heart and the soul
is supported and, and, and listened to.
And I do think that spelling
has given
that
gift to everyone. And it's opened my— Absolutely. Mind. I
already felt I had a pretty open mind and a
very open heart. And I've learned so much from this.
It's made your back wider. Yeah. And I will say
one of my favorite parts of
that of this time here was Peyton sitting on the
surfboard, and then he'd just stand up, and he kept
standing up. And what the Spellers and parents of Spellers
have taught me is that the, uh, you can get
in these loops.
And I'm watching and I'm videotaping, right? And he kept
standing up, and I thought, wait. And I had taken
Peyton here in 2020. And I got a picture of
him in 2020 where he was kneeling on the board,
and it just made me think,
hmm. And so I, I just gave a suggestion like,
hey, I think he's kind of in a, in a
loop,
like a motor loop. Like, and he clearly wants to
surf, so why not start him off on his knees?
Or then they end up standing up. Closer to standing
up. And, um, I was telling, I was telling Jody,
I'm like, What's the— and you, what's the— what's— what
can we call this? Because they'd start standing up. Start
standing. And it was, um,
standing start
for spelling surfers or something like that. That they— yeah,
it's different. And you listen and you got to really
think about what,
what they could use. Just like this, just like the
board, just like any means of communication. How can we
support? How can we include? How can we set them
up for success? Yeah. And the other thing I want
to do, I want to give a shout out to
this community, Wrightsville Beach. You know, we've been, we've been
out to, you know, restaurants. And again, everyone's been nothing
but supportive, accommodating, respectful. You know, it's been great. It's
just been super. Yeah. It's just, I think that, I
think that IndoJack Surf School has brought
a lot. It's just commonplace now. I mean, they've done
so much for
the community here just to show they, you know, worked
with wounded warriors,
all sorts of kids. Right. Yeah. Dave was telling me.
Yeah. Different groups. Yeah. So that's just, that's the legacy
of Indo Jax and we're just glad to be a
part of it. Yeah. I'm going to have, Dave's going
to be a guest on the podcast. We're going to
talk to him and other guests because they're doing some
amazing work. We would love to try to maybe do
something, bring it back to the Northwest.
You know, you just never know. We talk about, you
know, Dave talked about planting seeds and I love that
analogy. That's what we're doing is planting seeds here and
we'll see what springs up. So Kim, thank you for
including me,
inviting us, including me. I'm so glad I got to
like lure you, hurl you to the other coast after
I went to your coast. Yeah, that's right. We've been
on each other's coast the last couple of months. So
thank you. And again, thank you for those of you
who have joined us and we'll catch you next time
on the lighter side of the spectrum.